"Previously on The Mentalist..."
- Hello. You were watching me.
- Hi. Yes.
- Why?
- It's my job.
That was Erica Flynn.
She wants to help out with the investigation.
Great. We should fax over the case file
and get her a gun.
"You're skilled at getting people
to open up to you, to trust you"
and there's a question
whether you use that skill
to help people
or to manipulate them.
"You can't find happiness again,
even true love."
You have to be willing
to let me help you.
- Did you know Erica was gonna do this?
- Try to escape? Of course.
I know you have feelings for me.
This was a car bombing in Pakistan
14 months ago.
7 people died, 30 injured.
Egypt, eight months ago.
14 people killed.
This was an attack on a hotel in Indonesia.
All of these are made possible by this man...
Jan Nemec. Slovakian.
He was trained by
the Russian mob as a teenager.
He's based in Beirut now.
- So, he's part of a terrorist group?
- Not with a face like that.
- He's obviously in it for the money.
- Correct.
This is Danitra Cass.
She's C.I.A.
They're here to ask for your help
with the Nemec case.
Nemec's a supplier.
He sells weapons, explosives.
We've been struggling
to get solid intelligence on him for years.
But he's careful. Won't use computers,
doesn't leave a data trail.
Well, you must have something
or you wouldn't be here.
A source in Beirut
claims that Nemec
just sent a shipment
of passport chips to the U.S.
You use these chips
to forge passports
to get people in and out
of the country undetected.
Our informant says that
he was paid 1.5 million Euros
by a jihadist group
in the Philippines.
We think it's the first step
towards an attack on American soil.
We need to find these passport chips
and arrest Nemec
and that is why we're asking
for your help.
Actually, it's because of this woman.
- Erica Flynn?
- I understand you've dealt with her.
She ran a dating service in California.
We arrested her for killing her husband.
She escaped from prison about a year ago.
She's been on the run ever since.
Well, she ran into Nemec.
She's his girlfriend.
What exactly was your relationship
with her, Mr. Jane?
- Me? Why?
- Because we contacted Ms. Flynn
and she's agreed to help us
find the chips, arrest Nemec
in exchange for a reduced sentence
of her murder charge.
But she insists on working with you.
Says no other person will do.
- Excuse me.
- No other person will do.
Don't ask me.
Abbott, we got the link set up
in your office.
Okay, let's go.
Join us, please.
Erica Flynn's not asking to work with me.
Why am I a part of this?
Well, if Jane goes to Beirut
he's gonna need a partner
to go undercover with him.
You've done it before.
Seemed like a logical choice.
- Is there a problem?
- I arrested her.
I don't know how I feel
about helping her avoid prison.
Yeah, it's a... a tradeoff. I know
but it's worth it, I think,
with the issues at hand.
- Jane? Good.
- Me? No. No problem.
Well, Lisbon, if you still have concerns
we can discuss it after the meeting, okay?
Here we go.
Ms. Flynn,
everyone's here.
"Patrick. It's so good to see you.
And Agent Lisbon."
Hello.
- What is this about, Erica?
- "Isn't it obvious?"
- "I need you."
- Really?
"Jan uses a courier to send messages
but they're coded."
"The courier has to memorize
a long string of numbers."
"I can't think of anyone with a better
memory than yours."
Nemec's courier was killed in an accident.
He's looking for a new one.
He has to let the people
that bought the passport chips
know where to pick them up.
We'd like you to go to Beirut
and be the courier.
He'll give you the code, we'll crack it
get the chips, and him.
Well, I guess I could do that.
"Wonderful."
"See you when you get here."
"I look forward to working
with you again, Patrick."
Interesting woman.
Sir? There's no need to meet.
It's an important mission.
I'm happy to be a part of it.
It's no problem.
- No?
- None at all.
- So, we're all good, then?
- Yeah, we're good.
Thank you.
You know what they have here?
Great Orange blossom ice cream.
- Oh, that sounds good.
- Yeah, we'll get some.
- Here we are.
- Here we go.
Patrick. Welcome.
Teresa, it's so good to see you.
- Hi.
- Erica. I was wondering if you'd be here.
I thought we should talk
as soon as you got in.
- I hope you don't mind.
- Not at all.
I had them prepare tea.
So thoughtful.
- Teresa, may I?
- No, thanks.
So, the FBI.
That's quite an accomplishment.
Ms. Flynn, if you don't mind
I'd like to ask you a couple questions.
Of course.
Erica, please.
How did you get involved
with Jan Nemec?
It's kind of embarrassing, actually.
I ran into some trouble in Sao Paulo...
money trouble.
You're in a foreign country
cut off from everything you know.
You know how difficult it is
to live like that.
Well, I think you were born
You flatter me.
Jan was very charming,
and he wanted to help.
We started seeing each other,
fell into traveling together.
I didn't know what he does for a living.
He told me he was a businessman.
- And you believed him?
- He's very secretive about his work.
I suspected it was unsavory, maybe illegal
but not what it actually involves.
When the C.I.A. told me,
I was horrified.
And that's why you're turning him in...
because he horrifies you?
No. Mainly because
I wanna go back home.
- I miss it more than I thought I would.
- You're homesick.
Is that so strange?
When you were away,
weren't there things that you missed
that you would have given
anything to get back?
Yeah. There... there were.
I can see you don't
believe me, Teresa.
I just hope that in time
you'll see that I'm telling the truth.
We should go see Jan.
He's expecting you.
- Okay.
- Patrick has to go alone.
He's very suspicious.
He doesn't even know you're here.
- I don't think I like this.
- Don't worry. It'll... it'll be fine.
- Lead the way.
- Excuse me.
So, you and Lisbon are together,
as in a couple?
I can tell by the way
she looks at you
that you have more than
a professional relationship.
That is, in fact, correct, yes.
- I'm happy for you, Patrick.
- Thank you.
For both of you.
But especially for you.
I know how much you wanted love in your life.
I'm very happy you found it.
What is this really about, Erica?
- What do you mean?
- Why are you doing this?
I told you. I wanna go home.
Yes, but there's something else.
You're wrong.
But thank you for suspecting me.
Makes me feel very interesting.
These men will take you to Jan.
- Yes.
- Come.
- Guess I'll see you a little later.
- Good luck, Patrick.
Hi. I'm here to see Jan Nemec.
Where are we going?
I don't need to go to the bathroom.
Okay.
What... what is this?
What is... what is this,
all about here?
Listen guys, if you were
planning on scaring me
then mission accomplished.
I am... I'm scared.
Am I... am I gonna get to see
Mr. Nemec?
- Listen.
- I'm listening.
Listen. Helicopter.
Electric range. Newfoundland.
Albino. Retrovirus.
Wheelbarrow.
Okay, what... what...
Battery. Tractor. Fox.
Hypotenuse. Slender. Elm.
Stop! Stop, please. Stop.
Stone. Harmony.
Lint. Banana. Ladder.
Okay. Okay.
Patrick Jane, right?
Jan. Jan Nemec.
Sorry. That was pretty nasty, I know.
Still, I need you to repeat the words
he just said to you in order.
A towel.
- Yeah, sure. First the words.
- I want a towel.
Thank you.
Helicopter. Electric range.
Newfoundland.
Albino. Retrovirus.
Wheelbarrow. Battery.
Tractor.
Fox. Hypotenuse.
Slender. Elm. Stone.
Harmony. Lint. Banana.
Ladder.
Erica said your memory was good.
She's right.
- Just a trick.
- No, I tested others.
You're the only one
getting everything correct.
- I didn't say it was an easy trick.
- Like I said, uh, I'm sorry.
Please.
Let's have something to drink.
- I'd rather talk about the job.
- Nah. You don't want to have a drink?
What kind of a man are you, Jane?
Okay. The job.
I need you to carry
a message up here.
- What kind of message?
- 81 unrelated numbers.
You'll have to memorize them.
They cannot be written down.
When you get to the other end
you'll have to repeat them in precise order.
- Otherwise, it's useless.
- What does it mean? What's it about?
Oh, that's exactly the point.
You don't know.
- What are you paying?
- 10,000 Euros.
If it works out, there's gonna be more.
- 15,000.
- 10,000.
20,000, just for getting me wet.
- Get someone else. I'm not interested.
Erica said you were an actor.
- Sort of.
- And a policeman?
Yeah, I worked with the police.
There was something I wanted.
And when I got it, I left.
- Because you killed someone, she said.
- More than one... Actually.
But who's counting?
You know, if you want to check me
or look me up it's on the Internet.
Oh, we have... Patrick.
We have.
Relax. Everything looks okay.
Erica says you're a good guy.
It's all good.
I have only one question, though.
Who's this?
And, why is she with you?
Hi.
- Why are you wet?
- That's a little... gag of Jan's here.
Jan Nemec, this is my girlfriend,
Teresa Lisbon.
We traveled together.
So, uh... What are you doing
in Beirut?
- Patrick thought it would be a good idea.
- She has nothing to do with this.
- Could she just go back to the hotel please?
- You can ask me anything.
Well, maybe you can tell me
if you're with the FBI.
- No. Why?
- What?
Well, it says here, FBI website
there's a Special Agent Teresa Lisbon.
It's a mistake. That's crazy.
Check again.
What's that?
Someone's searching for Lisbon
in an FBI database.
- Is that a problem.
- No, we're set up for it.
- Different woman.
- Told you.
- Yeah.
- Sorry. Mistake.
- It's all right. No harm done.
- Yeah, well, we're going back to the hotel.
If you need to talk to me,
you know where to find me.
Metropole hotel.
Wylie suggested building
the fake profile.
"So, now when they see any other
mention of Teresa Lisbon"
"they'll assume it's that woman."
Tell Wylie I owe him one.
"So, what do you think?"
- Is Nemec on the hook?
- It's hard to tell.
Jane made an impression.
That we know.
We'll get back to you.
- Are you all right?
- Fine.
You have a lot of nerve
showing up here.
- What do you mean?
- You told Nemec about me.
It was you. You're the only one
who knows I'm here.
- Of course I did.
- Why?
- She's trying to gain Nemec's trust.
- Yes.
I've been trying to convince Jan
to hire Patrick.
He was suspicious,
so telling him about you
only helped prove
that I'm trustworthy.
- You should have told us.
- I'm sorry. I was working fast.
I assumed you would be prepared
for the possibility that
he would find out about you.
- We are.
- Good. Because it worked.
He's downstairs.
He's ready to make the deal.
Do you mind if I stay up here?
He doesn't want me down there.
Okay.
I'll be going.
Bye, y'all.
Get a little room service.
No, Patrick.
Okay. 20,000.
But I need you to go right away.
5,000 now.
15,000 when you come back.
- Where am I going?
- The U.S. Atlanta, Georgia.
You need to go tonight,
tomorrow at the latest.
When you get there,
call this number.
Guy who answers
will say his name is John Paul.
When he gives you that name,
you say "Dad sends his love."
He'll say "I miss him." That means
everything is fine and you can meet.
He'll tell you an address.
You go there, give him a message.
Job done.
What's the message?
Left to right, top to bottom,
in order.
- Can I have a few minutes?
- Yeah, sure.
Erica says you're the smartest
man she ever met.
Yeah.
Never heard her say that
about anyone else.
You had her, right?
- I'm working.
- Of course.
You speak Lebanese?
Just enough to say
"please" and "thank you."
- Would you like some?
- I'm good.
I hope you don't mind me saying so
but I'm very happy that you and Patrick
have found each other.
Patrick likes to pretend
that he's this lone wolf.
He's needed someone in his life
ever since his wife died.
I'm very glad it's you.
- Did he say something to you?
- I used to be a matchmaker.
I can tell when someone
is starting a new relationship.
It's a beautiful thing to see.
Well... Thanks.
I also sense some tension
between you and I.
And I really don't want that.
- You have nothing to worry about.
- Why would I worry? What?
- Did Patrick not say anything?
- About what?
I should have known.
So typical.
Men like to pretend
like the past never happened.
We're the ones who remember.
I shouldn't have said anything.
Please forgive me.
"54."
10.
300.
"28."
"6."
That's 81 numbers.
Mr. Jane, are you sure about these?
There's a lot hanging on this.
- Yes, I'm sure.
- All right. We got it from here, buddy.
You got a plane to catch tomorrow.
Lay low, okay?
Will do.
You know, I'm not that tired.
How about you?
- No.
- Want to go get something to eat?
Bellboy was telling me about this restaurant
that does a great "manakish".
Yeah, sure.
- Everything okay?
- Fine.
Okay.
Your liaison... give him the numbers
and any other support that they ask for.
Tell Vega to stay close
and give you the help you need.
Got it.
- And what if they can't crack it?
- What are you thinking?
This guy, John Paul
does he have any idea when Jane's
supposed to arrive in the U.S.?
No. And Nemec won't risk
getting in touch with him.
Jane said he was only given a window
of arrival, not a specific date.
So, as far as he knows,
Jane's already here.
- Does he know what Jane looks like?
- No. He doesn't.
So, let's set up the meet.
We get the message to John Paul
we follow him to the location
we grab him and the passport chips
even if he can't crack the code.
- Is that okay with the C.I.A.?
- As long as we're in on it.
Our pleasure.
- This is John Paul.
- Dad sends his love.
- I miss him.
- Where should I go?
- You're in Atlanta?
- Yes.
"How soon can you meet?"
Five hours.
There's a roadhouse
in Brookhaven.
Little Ed's on Walthrop.
- Turn your coffee cup upside down.
- Okay.
Fire up the jet.
So, anyway, the analysts are trying
something called modulo-2 arithmetic
which sounds very cool.
I just wish I knew what it meant.
Hello?
- Sorry, uh, what were you saying?
- Nothing.
Looks like they're getting ready
for the meet.
Yep.
- Pretty exciting, I guess.
- Yeah.
Anyway, how can I help you here?
You should go with Cho.
I don't need your help.
- No.
- No, don't worry.
It's fine. Don't worry about it.
- You mean it?
- Yeah. Sure.
- Thank you. You're the best.
- Of course.
Sir.
Agent Wylie doesn't need my help.
Okay if I come along with you?
You run it by Abbott?
Did he okay it?
- Yes, sir, he did.
- Suit up. We leave right away.
Only two minutes past the target hour.
Everybody stay loose.
Male, 30s, from the north.
- There she is.
- Hey!
False alarm.
Another male.
Late 20s, possibly Filipino.
Hey. Hey, everybody stay calm.
You bitch!
Vega!
- You okay?
- Yeah.
Oh, thank you.
What?
What was that thing
you said was good?
- It was mana something?
- Manakish.
Yeah, it's like a little pizza.
- What's up?
- Nothing.
Nothing.
Did something happen
between you and Erica Flynn?
Why?
She made a point of letting me
know that it did, so did it?
Well, um...
Actually, yes.
Something did.
When we were working
together, we... we kissed.
- You kissed?
- Just once in her hotel room.
- This story just keeps on getting better.
- It was nothing.
- Don't say that, okay?
- Okay, well, you're right.
It... it wasn't nothing at the time.
But it was a long time ago,
and, um...
It was never gonna amount to anything.
It just... it... it couldn't.
- Why didn't you tell me?
- I didn't think about it.
Well, when you found out we were coming here
you could have told me.
Yes, I thought about it then
but I... I made a decision... not to tell you
because I was worried that, um...
That it would come between us.
I just wish I'd heard it from you first.
That's all.
I understand.
Yeah, uh... I should have told you.
- I'm sorry.
- It's okay.
Really. It's okay.
Are there any others
that I should know about?
Like, people we've worked with? It would...
it would help me if I... if I knew.
- No.
- Lorelei?
I always thought that maybe
something happened with you two.
Lorelei?
Okay, how about this?
I'll tell you about Lorelei
if you would tell me
about one Walter Mashburn.
You said that manakish
is like a little pizza?
- Yeah, that's right.
- Yum.
- Let's get some.
- Yeah.
- Tea?
- Please.
Is that your phone?
- What's up, boss?
- "We've got a problem."
"His full name
is John Paul Navarro."
Looks like he was connected
to a jihadist group in the Philippines.
- We're still looking into that.
- "What about the blank passport chips?"
Well, looks like they're in the Atlanta area
but we just don't know where.
How's the C.I.A. doing with the code?
They can't crack it.
They think it's a one-time pad.
- What's that?
- "It's a-a code made with a key."
The person who encodes
the message has the key
so does the person
who decodes it.
Without it, you can't make sense of it.
Nemec and John Paul must have the key.
Did you check John Paul's apartment?
Yeah, but we need to know
what we're looking for.
It could be anything...
a magazine, a book.
- It's a book.
- "Why?"
Well, Nemec has two bookshelves
filled, and he's not a reader.
We still need to know
which book it is.
So, in the meantime,
you two need to get out of there.
Pretty soon, Nemec is gonna find out
that John Paul is dead, and when he does
you two need to
stay out of sight.
Change hotels, stay indoors
"and get on that plane
tomorrow."
Yeah, we'll definitely do all of that
but I think we can find
those computer chips.
- How?
- I'll tell you later. Bye.
What's your plan?
The key is probably in one of the books
in Nemec's apartment.
I just need to figure out which one.
Well, how are we gonna
get into the apartment?
- Taxi!
- Don't tell me you're calling her.
- I am. Yes, we do.
- We don't need her help.
Hey, Erica, it's Patrick.
Sorry to wake you.
Yep. Yep.
Jan's got a meeting across town.
It should be fine.
- Do you need help?
- Uh, yeah.
No, actually. I...
I'm... I'm fine, thank you.
- Do you know what you're looking for?
- Sort of.
I always think of you as having a plan
but never admitting it.
That's funny.
That's how I think of you.
- How much longer?
- Not too much longer. Be patient.
He's here. He's back.
Light. Light, light, light, light.
I think we're fine.
Whew! That was close.
- I'm sorry you didn't get your book.
- Oh, no. I got... I got my book.
Right here.
Let's go.
- Excuse me, sir?
- Yeah, what do you got?
Well, the C.I.A. analysts think the code
treats each book page like a grid
so the first number
tells you what page number
the second's the number
of letters across the bottom
the third's the number
of letters up.
Each three-number set
gives you one letter.
- Yeah, how long to work it out?
- If they're right, 10 minutes.
Call Cho as soon as you got it.
FBI! Open up!
"Clear!"
Clear!
"Clear upstairs!"
Doesn't look like
anybody's been here for a while.
You sure your people
got the right address?
- Any sign of the chips upstairs?
- No. But they're looking.
Maybe we want to bring in some techs
start tearing up the floorboards.
They could be anywhere.
- Are the shades drawn upstairs?
- I think so.
This one isn't.
Guess this is the right address.
That's great. What about the group
John Paul belonged to?
Did we get anything on them?
From what we can tell
most of the membership's in the Philippines.
Pretty low level, barely on the radar
but we have our eyes on them now.
Tell me, how did Jane know
which book it was?
It had to have been a book
that Nemec had read recently
so he looked for one
that had a cracked spine
that didn't have any dust on it.
Nice. Nemec in custody yet?
The Beirut police
are arresting him now.
You think you get away?!
I'll find you, Erica!
I'll find you!
I'll cut off your head and I'll spit
down your neck you little bitch!
Jane?
I was just helping Erica
for a moment.
Helping her?
Yes. Jan was furious.
It was very upsetting.
Okay.
A Beirut police officer will take you
into protective custody
until the embassy can arrange for you
to be escorted back to the U.S.
Okay. That's fine.
- Jane, can I talk to you for a second?
- Sure.
- Look, Lisbon, she's just very upset.
- Well, I don't want to talk about her.
This is about you.
You lied about kissing her.
I didn't lie.
And you insisted on getting her help
even after I specifically asked you not to.
I'm working with her.
That's what we're supposed to do, right?
Ever since we got here,
you're talking about Erica
trying to find ways
to spend time with her.
Lisbon, there's no reason to get
emotional here. It's... it's... it's nothing.
Whatever happened
between you two, it's not over.
- Just admit it.
- That is not true. It's not.
I need to bring Nemec in with the police.
You do what you want. I'm done.
I guess this is the officer that's
supposed to take you into custody.
- He's not going to, is he?
- No.
- You always have every angle covered.
- Don't you?
- It's here, isn't it?
- What?
That thing you wouldn't tell me about...
the other reason you did this.
I'm sorry. I don't know
what you're talking about.
The 1.5 million euro Nemec received
for those passport chips.
The money... it's in this room.
You needn't deny it.
You're the smartest man I ever met.
- It's pretty, isn't it?
- Gorgeous.
You took your chance
when the C.I.A. came to you
about turning Nemec in.
Then you had his courier killed
and you made it look like
it was an accident.
Why do you always think
the worst of me?
And you thought that you could use me
to take care of Nemec and take his cash.
After all, you'd already gotten
away from me once before.
You never intended
to go back to the U.S.
All you wanted was Nemec's money
and freedom.
- Maybe you're not as smart as I thought.
- Why would you say that?
- It wasn't just about the money.
- What else?
I missed you, Patrick.
I'm a professional in the field of romance
and relationships.
And it pains me to admit it,
but in my professional opinion
- you and Lisbon will not last as a couple.
- Why is that?
Because you're drawn to each other
for the wrong reasons.
You're attracted to her virtue, her honesty
and her goodness...
things you think you lack.
She's interested in you for your danger
your unpredictability, your transgressions.
These superficial qualities
are alluring, even erotic
but they don't make
for a lasting relationship.
- And what does?
- Finding your soul mate...
the person who sees the world
the way you do
who laughs at the things
you laugh at and...
wants the things that you want.
- And that's you?
- Here I am.
I love Lisbon.
And I'm taking you
to the real police
and they're gonna lock you up
for the rest of your life.
Oh, Patrick.
I tried.
Goodbye.
On your knees, Erica.
Do it.
Jane, you all right?
Yeah. Yep.
I'm okay, just...
Oh, just need to walk it off
a little bit.
- "Lisbon sent this?"
- Yeah.
- What's gonna happen to her?
- Abbott says the deal's off.
When she gets back, she'll serve
out the rest of her sentence.
Vega.
- Come here.
- Yes, sir.
Sit down.
You did good work today.
But Abbott says he never approved you
leaving the office. You said he did.
Did you lie to me?
- Sir, I di...
- Answer the question.
Yes. I'm sorry.
I know that...
I just got excited, I guess
- and I thought that I'd be a lot more...
- That's not your call.
Now, I can't work with someone
I can't trust.
- You can trust me.
- No, I can't.
You're not going out
in the field with me again.
- For how long?
- We'll see.
Hey.
You okay?
What are we doing?
- We need to get to the airport.
- Come on. You'll see.
It says we have to be there
two hours early.
Oh, my God. Jane!
It's amazing.
- You did this?
- Of course.
- Please.
- Thank you.
- And...
- What?
Orange blossom ice cream.
You are good.
- Dig in.
- Thank you.
- What's that?
- Fireworks.
Fireworks?
It's the end of Ramadan.
They're celebrating.
Fireworks. Beautiful.
Yeah. It is beautiful.
- You thought it was a bomb, didn't you?
- No, I didn't.
- Yes, you did.
- I did not.
You did.
You know, this ice cream
is only just okay.
Don't take it out
on the ice cream.
I'm just saying, it's a long way to go
for an okay bowl of ice cream.
As they say, you can take
the girl out of Chicago
but you can't take the Chicago
out of the girl.